Finding Aid for Edward Ginsberg papers, 1950-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Edward Ginsberg papers 1950-1997 1957-1980
Ginsberg, Edward, 1917-1997.
2012069 Aa 2
Edward Ginsberg was born in Brooklyn in 1917 and graduated from the University of Michigan in 1938. Ginsberg was heavily involved in Israeli and Jewish activities in the United States and served as chairman and president of United Jewish Appeal. The collection primarily documents his travel to Israel on behalf of United Jewish Appeal and highlights his relationship with prominent Israeli leaders, including Golda Meir, Moshe Dayan, and David Ben-Gurion. The collection is especially strong in its visual documentation of life in Israel during the 1960s.
7 linear feet
12 film reels
9 items
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by the Robert Ginsberg Family and William and Inger Ginsberg (donor no. 10746 ) in March 2012.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Edward Ginsberg was born in Brooklyn, New York in 1917 and then moved with his family to Cleveland, Ohio. He received a Bachelor of Arts from the University of Michigan in 1938 and a Juris Doctor from Harvard University in 1941. After graduation, he returned to Cleveland, where he practiced law for more than 50 years.
Throughout his life, Mr. Ginsberg devoted himself to Israeli and Jewish activities in the U.S. and around the world. After World War II, he played an important role raising funds for the establishment and support of the State of Israel, working directly with world figures including Golda Meir and Yitzhak Rabin.
In the 1960s and 70s, Mr. Ginsberg was a general chairman and then president of United Jewish Appeal, and president of the American Joint Distribution Committee. Mr. Ginsberg was also vice president of the Jewish Telegraphic Agency and a founder of the Cleveland Jewish News. He served as a life trustee of the Jewish Community Federation of Cleveland, was past president of the Fairmount Temple, and sponsored many educational programs at Hebrew University of Jerusalem. Hebrew Union College and Hebrew University in Jerusalem awarded him honorary degrees, Hebrew University made him an honorary founder, and the Jewish Community Federation awarded him the Eisenman Award for humanitarianism. He was involved in many business activities, including directorships of El Al Israel Airlines and the First Israel Bank and Trust Company. A lifelong sports enthusiast, he was a partner in the New York Yankees and a past director in the Chicago Bulls.
The Ginsberg Center at the University of Michigan, which supports community service and learning, was endowed in Ginsberg's honor. The Rosalie Ginsberg scholarship -- named for Mr. Ginsberg's wife -- is also awarded annually to students with financial need who are dedicated to community service. The Rosalie Ginsberg Awards honors those who have made exceptional contributions to society, on campus and beyond, through exemplary engagements in service and social action.
Ginsberg died in 1997.
The Edward Ginsberg papers document Ginsberg's involvement with United Jewish Appeal and his relationship with prominent Israeli politicians, including Golda Meir, Moshe Dayan, and David Ben Gurion. The collection is primarily composed of photographs and films covering Ginsberg's travels to Israel on behalf of United Jewish Appeal. These photographs offer strong visual evidence of life in Israel during the 1960s and following the Six Days War.
The collection is organized in five series: Autographed Books (1 linear foot); Travel and Events (2 linear feet); Photographs and Slides (2 linear feet); Motion Pictures (2.5 linear feet and 12 reels), Audiotapes (.5 linear feet); and Awards and Memorabilia (.2 linear feet and 9 oversized items).
Subjects:
Ben-Gurion, David, 1886-1973.; Dayan, Moshe, 1915-1981.; Ginsberg, Edward, 1917-1997.; Meir, Golda, 1898-1978.; Jews--Israel.; Jews, American--Travel--Israel.; American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee.; United Jewish Appeal.; Israel.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Allon, Yigal 1918-1980.; Ben-Gurion, David, 1886-1973.; Dayan, Moshe, 1915-1981.; Ginsberg, Edward, 1917-1997.; Meir, Golda, 1898-1978.; Jews--Israel.; Travel--Ethiopia.; Travel--Iran.; Travel--Israel.; Travel--Morocco.; Zionism.; Israel.; American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee.; United Jewish Appeal.
Genre Terms:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.
- Autographed Books
  The Autographed Books series contains books signed by prominent Israeli cultural and political figures, including Golda Meir, Moshe Dayan, and David Ben-Gurion.
  - A Land of Our Own-- by Golda Meir, 1973 (signed by Golda Meir) (Box 1)
  - Break-Through-- by Moshe Dayan, 1981 (signed by Moshe Dayan) (Box 1)
  - Days of David Ben-Gurion, 1967 (signed by David Ben-Gurion) (Box 1)
  - From the Beginning: Archaeology and Art in the Israel Museum, 1968 (signed by David Harris) (Box 1)
  - Historical Sites in Israel-- by Moshe Pearlman and Yaacov Yannai, 1965 (signed by Levi Eshkol) (Box 1)
  - Israel Journal: June 1967-- by Yaël Dayan, 1967 (signed by Yaël Dayan) (Box 1)
  - Israel: The Reality-- edited by Cornell Capa, 1969 (signed by Cornell Capa) (Box 1)
  - Land of Israel-- photos by Beno Rothenberg, 1958 (signed by David Ben-Gurion) (Box 1)
  - Moshe Dayan: A Portrait--edited by Pinchas Jurman, 1968 (signed by Moshe Dayan) (Box 1)
  - My Life-- by Golda Meir, 1975 (signed by Golda Meir) (Box 1)
  - My People: The Story of the Jews-- by Abba Eban, 1968 (signed by Abba Eban) (Box 1)
  - Shield of David: The Story of Israel's Armed Forces-- by Yigal Allon, 1970 (signed by Yigal Allon) (Box 1)
- Travel and Events
  The Travel and Events series is primarily composed of black and white photographs, but also includes invitations, copies of remarks, and various items from Ginsberg's trips abroad. The series documents trips taken on behalf of the American Jewish Distribution Committee and United Jewish Appeal in addition to personal travel.
  - American Jewish Distribution Committee
    - Iran Trip 1973, includes black and white photographs (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, includes black and white photographs (Box 2)
  - Israel Trip 1970, includes black and white photographs with photographs with Moshe Dayan and Golda Meir (Box 2)
  - Jewish Community Federation, includes black and white photographs (Box 2)
  - Personal Travel
    - Ethiopia (Box 2)
    - France (Box 2)
    - Italy, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Ocean Liners (Box 2)
    - Vienna (Box 2)
  - United Jewish Appeal
    - 25th Anniversary (Box 2)
    - 30th Anniversary (Box 2)
    - 1963 Mission
      - Photographs-- General (Box 2)
      - Photographs-- Poland (Box 2)
      - "Progress and Problems (Box 2)
    - 1964 Mission, includes black and white photographs (Box 2)
    - 1966 Mission, includes black and white photographs (Box 2)
    - 1968 Mission, includes black and white photographs (Box 2)
    - 1970 Mission, includes black and white photographs (Box 2)
    - Israel Trip 1968, album (Box 2)
    - Or Yehuda Trip 1969, album (Box 2)
    - Golda Meir Dinner
      - Photographs, 1970 (Box 2)
      - Remarks 1970 (Box 2)
    - Levi Eshkol Dinner 1968 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, includes black and white photographs (Box 2)
  - White House 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous
    - American Jewish Congress 1973 (Box 2)
    - Hebrew University of Jerusalem (Box 2)
    - "We Are All" article 1969 (Box 2)
    - World Series Program 1950 (Box 2)
- Photographs and Slides
  The Photographs and Slides series is composed of photographs and slides that are not associated with a specific trip taken by Ginsberg. These photographs are mainly taken in Israel and include pictures of Ginsberg with Moshe Dayan, David Ben Gurion, Golda Meir, and Yigal Allon. This series also includes Ginsberg family photographs.
  - Family (Box 3)
  - David Ben-Gurion (Box 3)
  - Moshe Dayan (Box 3)
  - Golda Meir (Box 3)
  - Golda Meir and Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Golda Meir, Yigal Allon, and Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous slides (Box 4)
- Motion Pictures
  The Motion Picture series includes films of Ginsberg's trips abroad, including Israel, Iran, and parts of Africa. The films are primarily 8 mm and 16 mm reels.
  - 16 mm Film
    - Europe #1 1955
      (Reel #1)
    - Europe #2 1955
      (Reel #2)
    - Israel 1957
      (Reel #3)
    - Unlabeled
      (Reel #4)
    - Iran, India, Thailand #1
      (Reel #5)
    - Iran, India, Thailand #2
      (Reel #6)
    - Morocco 1964
      (Reel #7)
    - Target Peace 1968
      (Reel #8)
    - Target Peace 1968
      (Reel #9)
    - Unlabeled
      (Reel #10)
    - Unlabeled
      (Reel #11)
    - Travel (Brazil, Bergen, Dusseldorf, Berlin, Switzerland, Yvoir)
      (Reel #12)
    - Egypt and Jordan 1967, 2 film reels (Box 5)
    - Ethiopia 1970, 4 film reels (Box 5)
    - Unlabeled, 11 reels (Box 5)
  - 8 mm motion picture (Box 6)
    - Africa 1973, 3 film reels (Box 6)
    - Australia 1980, 4 reels (Box 6)
    - China 1979, 3 film reels (Box 6)
      (includes list of shots)
    - Norway 1980, 3 reels (Box 6)
- Audio Tapes
  The Audiotapes includes audio recordings of events Ginsberg attended and events held in Ginsberg's honor.
  - David Ben-Gurion Birthday Party (Box 7)
  - Eban Meeting 1959, 2 reels (Box 7)
  - Hartford Big Fits 1968 (Box 7)
  - Testimonial Dinner -- Edward Ginsberg Remarks 1968 (Box 7)
  - United Jewish Appeal Dinner in Honor of Levi Eshkol -- Remarks of Edward Ginsberg 1968 (Box 7)
  - United Jewish Appeal Testimonial to Edward Ginsberg
    - Remarks of Edward Ginsberg 1967 (Box 7)
    - Recording of Dinner 1967, 2 reels (Box 7)
- Awards, Memorabilia, and Prints
  The Awards, Memorabilia, and Prints series is comprised of awards given to Ginsberg and memorabilia collected by him. This series includes a scrapbook documenting Ginsberg's travel for United Jewish Appeal, a framed print of Moshe Dayan, and a number of awards given to Ginsberg by the Israeli government and signed by Israeli Prime Ministers. The majority of items in this series are oversized and remain in their original frames.
  - Memorial Resolution on Edward Ginsberg 1997 (Box 7)
  - Fellow of Education (Box 7)
  - University of Michigan Commencement 1938 (Box 7)
  - Scrapbook (Volume 1)
  - Citations and visual materials
    - Autographed pictures (includes Chaim Bar-Lev, Golda Meir), framed photograph
    - Charles Eisenman Award 1971, framed photograph
    - Hebrew Union College Honorary Degree 1972, framed photograph
    - Hebrew University of Jerusalem Honorary Fellow 1971, framed photograph
    - Moshe Dayan print, framed photograph
    - "Operation Emergency", framed photograph
    - White House dinner with Golda Meir 1973, framed photograph
    - White House dinner with Yitzhak Rabin 1974, framed photograph